<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-02-24T17:15:15+05:30</updated><id>/feed.xml</id><entry><title type="html">Dealgorithmizing my life - 3</title><link href="/2021/02/15/Dealgorithmizing-my-life-3.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dealgorithmizing my life - 3" /><published>2021-02-15T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2021-02-15T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>/2021/02/15/Dealgorithmizing-my-life-3</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2021/02/15/Dealgorithmizing-my-life-3.html">&lt;p&gt;This is going to be my last blog post on this topic. I’ve been dealgorithmizing for more than a week now, and as with anything, there were highs and lows in the process. The idea of dealgorithmization has matured a little more in head over this period of time. I realized that I had no real reason to hate every single algorithm (since that would just be stupid); it was the unproductive algorithms I had a problem with. Part of what makes this problem hard is the definition of “productivity”. It means something different for everyone, and calling something “unproductive” is entirely subjective. Most people have the same notion about YouTube’s algorithms, which is that they are unproductive and more often than not, lead to long sessions of binge-watching your favorite YouTube series or your favorite creator’s content on the platform. But for a YouTuber/streamer, this wouldn’t really be unproductive as it could as a teaching tool for them to improve/diversify their content, or for commentary channels, as the fuel to keep the channel going.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also came to the conclusion that the cause of the algorithms being “unproductive” may not really be a problem with the algorithm itself. The recommender systems for platforms like YouTube and Spotify will (obviously) move towards what you &lt;em&gt;want&lt;/em&gt; to watch. That would be perfectly fine if the majority of the content on these platforms are what &lt;em&gt;you&lt;/em&gt; would consider “productive”. However, for those of us who don’t, the functioning of these algorithms and the sheer number and diversity of the content on these platforms would mainly just lead to unproductive videos being recommended to us. I say “mainly” because sometimes YouTube does recommend interesting and educational videos like &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=dxRB4sdbIcw&quot;&gt;this one&lt;/a&gt;. The reason why most people’s recommended sections are considered unproductive is simply because what we want to watch is not necessarily what we need to watch in order to be productive, especially since the majority of us use YouTube recreationally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-highs&quot;&gt;The Highs&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will admit that I was not completely successful in achieving my goal. I successfully dealgorithmized for 5 days out of 8. These 5 days were days in which I felt clear-headed and in control. This sounds a little trivial, but for me, who has OCD, it felt really good, as one moment of non-control could send my day spiraling down into the darkest depths of the void. This clear-headedness has led to more emotionally stable days, where I actually feel more active and feel like there is something to be done, and that the day has a purpose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have discovered some useful stuff in the time I’ve been carrying out this little project of mine. If you’ve not read the last blog post (or don’t care to), &lt;a href=&quot;https://newpipe.net/&quot;&gt;Newpipe&lt;/a&gt; has been really helpful. &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/sheensantoscapadngan/SpotaFree&quot;&gt;Spotafree&lt;/a&gt; is also a really interesting app that has helped me dealgorithmize. For podcasts, I’ve been using &lt;a href=&quot;https://antennapod.org/&quot;&gt;AntennaPod&lt;/a&gt; which is a really convenient podcast manager.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d describe these days as “fulfilling”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-lows&quot;&gt;The Lows&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other 3 days were pretty bad, to say the least. Usually, my mornings were wasted watching YouTube videos. Whenever I decided to get some work done, I succumbed to the temptation of (you guessed it!) a YouTube video. One morning, I decided to meditate for a bit, but made the mistake of checking Spotify for a new podcast to listen to before I sat down to meditate. What happened next is as predictable as a Dhar Mann video; I spent the entire morning just listening to music. As a musician, I wouldn’t consider that entirely unproductive, but it just wasn’t what I wanted to do that morning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A shitty morning spiraled into a shitty day, because for the whole day, my attitude became, “Fuck it. I watched crap tons of YouTube already. A little more isn’t going to hurt.” If I didn’t watch anything, there was hope, but even the slightest YouTube-watching led a potentially amazing day to lose all its potential for amazingness. After long wasted mornings, the day generally felt like it was permanently “tainted”; like a normal day couldn’t unfold because the morning had been thrown away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d describe these days as “hopeless”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;what-i-learned&quot;&gt;What I learned&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Demonizing anything isn’t very helpful, regardless of circumstance. The realization of there being productive and unproductive algorithms really helped as it provided a strong foundation to the “why” behind dealgorithmizing. As time passed, the idea of dealgorithmization got simpler and simpler in my head, which is good because in the immortal words of Mr. Terry Davis, “An idiot admires complexity. A genius admires simplicity.” Now, instead of a complex mess of words and concepts, I have a general intuition of what dealgorithmizing is about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end, it’s all about whether you think the platform you’re using helps you in doing what you would like to do. If watching videos on YouTube benefits you, watch as much YouTube as you want. If you’re not susceptible to short-term dopamine hits, and love watching things that will benefit you in the long run, then congratulations! You have harnessed the capability of the algorithm and have made it work in your favor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found that I am a slave to short-term happiness, often causing a decline in my ability to achieve that long-term happiness found most commonly through work. This is why I chose to dealgorithmize.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope this series of blog posts helped you in some way, and I wish you good luck in whatever you choose to do.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">This is going to be my last blog post on this topic. I’ve been dealgorithmizing for more than a week now, and as with anything, there were highs and lows in the process. The idea of dealgorithmization has matured a little more in head over this period of time. I realized that I had no real reason to hate every single algorithm (since that would just be stupid); it was the unproductive algorithms I had a problem with. Part of what makes this problem hard is the definition of “productivity”. It means something different for everyone, and calling something “unproductive” is entirely subjective. Most people have the same notion about YouTube’s algorithms, which is that they are unproductive and more often than not, lead to long sessions of binge-watching your favorite YouTube series or your favorite creator’s content on the platform. But for a YouTuber/streamer, this wouldn’t really be unproductive as it could as a teaching tool for them to improve/diversify their content, or for commentary channels, as the fuel to keep the channel going.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Dealgorithmizing my life - 2</title><link href="/2021/02/10/Dealgorithmizing-my-life-2.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dealgorithmizing my life - 2" /><published>2021-02-10T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2021-02-10T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>/2021/02/10/Dealgorithmizing-my-life-2</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2021/02/10/Dealgorithmizing-my-life-2.html">&lt;p&gt;As society comes ever closer to a dystopia, one must ask oneself the important questions, the questions that determine the priority of certain things in one’s life. These are the questions whose answers are the saving grace for some and the blow of death for the others. These are the questions whose answers decide what shall be left behind in the dirt, and what shall rise like a phoenix from the flame, enduring all that was thrown at it in the process of the world being mangled by the iron jaws of tyranny. “Philosophizing vs. Engineering”, “Idealism vs. Pragmatism”, “Minecraft vs. Fortnite”; questions like these determine the direction humanity will head in, and whether it will liberate itself from those iron jaws. When it comes to “YouTube vs. Newpipe”, I have chosen my side. Though the dystopia is inevitable, one can seek to delay it, which is why I side with Newpipe. It is the new coming of the light and shall push back against the evil that is YouTube for a long time to come, so long as we support it and are there to help it walk the path of light, to pull it back when it strays off the beaten path. Come, my friend, join us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Newpipe is an amazing solution to YouTube’s recommendation system and its privacy issues. It does not recommend stuff to you (even if it does, please don’t tell me) and works by scraping the videos off of YouTube, so no Google libraries are needed! I’ve been using &lt;a href=&quot;https://newpipe.net/&quot;&gt;Newpipe&lt;/a&gt; thanks to &lt;a href=&quot;https://joelchrono12.netlify.app/newpipe-over-vanced/&quot;&gt;this blog post&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&quot;https://fosstodon.org/web/accounts/210111&quot;&gt;@joeligj12@fosstodon.org&lt;/a&gt;. It’s amazing and is literally everything I needed (although I’m still going to limit myself to 5 videos per day).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;why-dealgorithmize-on-spotify&quot;&gt;Why dealgorithmize on Spotify?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although Spotify’s algorithms aren’t as bad as YouTube’s, they still are algorithms that are made (at least in part) with the intention of holding the user’s attention for as long as possible. Even though, in my experience, Spotify hasn’t been as guilty as YouTube when it comes to manipulating a user’s attention, I have recently found it very hard to do things without listening to music or a podcast (mostly manual labor and exercise). It’s that sort of dependency on these platforms that I would like to get away from, and the reason I’d like to ‘dealgorithmize’ is because this dependency on a platform’s content is usually because of the influence of its algorithms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;delving-into-the-specifics&quot;&gt;Delving into the specifics&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“When one wants a solution to a zoomer problem, one must think like a boomer.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;                                        - Sun Tzu, popular twitch streamer
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most obvious solutions to this problem is to just buy and download the music the boomer way, and this solution is most probably the way I’m going to go. The extra step of buying the music helps in reducing the flow of fuel that is fed to that over-saturated feedback loop that makes us want to keep scrolling in search of new stuff to listen to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“But how will you discover new music now?”, I hear you ask. Never fear my little child, for recommender systems are not the only way a human learns about new things, although it may seem that way sometimes. I’m going to buy a few random songs each time I buy some songs that I want. It’s a fun little way to experiment with different music genres to find songs that I like. I like to think that I’m pretty open-minded, and don’t base my criteria for liking music on whether it’s of a particular genre or not (i.e. being genre-ist), but on whether it sounds good to me. When it comes to this sort of stuff, I have a very simple philosophy - I like what I like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it comes to podcasts, I’m going to start listening to them on &lt;a href=&quot;https://newpipe.net/&quot;&gt;Newpipe&lt;/a&gt; (thanks again &lt;a href=&quot;https://fosstodon.org/web/accounts/210111&quot;&gt;@joeligj12@fosstodon.org&lt;/a&gt;). I have a long list of podcasts provided to me by &lt;a href=&quot;https://fosstodon.org/web/accounts/281292&quot;&gt;@sotolf@fosstodon.org&lt;/a&gt;, plus I’m also going to actively be searching for stuff that I like/want to listen to, either by DuckDuckGoing it, or by asking online communities about it (only when I want to of course, because one of the keywords in my long ramblings about this stuff has to be ‘choice’) so I’m pretty much covered in the ‘discovery’ department.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;two-problems&quot;&gt;Two problems&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Does the problem really lie in having the music/podcasts at your fingertips? If you remember, I said my problem with Spotify is that I have become dependent on it to perform daily tasks or to exercise. I simply have to have a podcast on or some music on while I’m doing these things. Is this a problem with having these things be easily available? And if so, how am I solving the problem? Because one can argue that by downloading the music, I have the same ease of access to it as I do with Spotify. Is it a problem with the music/podcasts themselves being addictive? In short, could my assumption of “algorithms are causing us to be dependent on these services” be wrong?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t think the problem is with the easy access to content. I also don’t think the problem is in how addictive a piece of content is. I think the problem is in platforms like Spotify not giving us the choice to control what we’re able to see. When I deal with downloaded music/podcasts, I have the choice to delete them when I feel I’m getting too dependent on them. I have the choice to bring the factor of difficulty (redownloading music/podcasts) into the equation. But when it comes to Spotify, I have no choice to stop recommendations. I have no say in controlling what I want to see. The only option I have is to stop using the app. All I’m doing is simply switching to another platform which gives me the option to control what I’m able to see.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;goodbye-spotify-im-going-spotifree-now&quot;&gt;Goodbye Spotify, I’m going Spotifree now.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(worst joke ever told)&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">As society comes ever closer to a dystopia, one must ask oneself the important questions, the questions that determine the priority of certain things in one’s life. These are the questions whose answers are the saving grace for some and the blow of death for the others. These are the questions whose answers decide what shall be left behind in the dirt, and what shall rise like a phoenix from the flame, enduring all that was thrown at it in the process of the world being mangled by the iron jaws of tyranny. “Philosophizing vs. Engineering”, “Idealism vs. Pragmatism”, “Minecraft vs. Fortnite”; questions like these determine the direction humanity will head in, and whether it will liberate itself from those iron jaws. When it comes to “YouTube vs. Newpipe”, I have chosen my side. Though the dystopia is inevitable, one can seek to delay it, which is why I side with Newpipe. It is the new coming of the light and shall push back against the evil that is YouTube for a long time to come, so long as we support it and are there to help it walk the path of light, to pull it back when it strays off the beaten path. Come, my friend, join us.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Dealgorithmizing my life - 1</title><link href="/2021/02/07/Dealgorithmizing-my-life-1.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dealgorithmizing my life - 1" /><published>2021-02-07T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2021-02-07T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>/2021/02/07/Dealgorithmizing-my-life-1</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2021/02/07/Dealgorithmizing-my-life-1.html">&lt;p&gt;As I listen to a mathematician analyze a Minecraft YouTuber’s speedrun, I think to myself, “Is this the most productive I can be?” And as I begin to reflect upon this question, I try to recollect how I got to this point. The last thing I remembered was being separated from my parents and put into a small cramped room. The people who put me there told me that all I had to do was to look at a screen, and so I did. But I never recalled time passing by so fast; had it really been 20 years?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;dealing-with-youtube&quot;&gt;Dealing with YouTube&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;YouTube probably has the most infamous algorithm out there. Recommendations of COOM material is not unheard of during the sacred time that is No Nut November. On a more serious note, YouTube is the one of the biggest hurdles on the track to a productive life (at least for me). A HUGE part of my day is wasted just looking for a video to watch. I used to get up in the morning to exercise and meditate, but now, after getting up in the morning, I just browse through YouTube trying to find something to entertain me. Suffice it to say, YouTube’s recommendation system is really effective at getting people to waste their time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d also like to address the question, “What if it’s not a problem with YouTube, but a lack of willpower on the user’s part?” I really don’t get that question, since it’s like saying that if someone much stronger than you punches you, just stop the punch. Firstly, why should the stronger person punch the weaker person in the first place? Here, the stronger person is likened to YouTube’s algorithm (and other recommender systems as well), and the weaker one to the user. Secondly, I have no doubt that the user is the weaker person in this analogy. Thousands of dollars and thousands of people have contributed to creating an algorithm meant to make you sit and stare at a screen for hours on end. You simply CANNOT win against this. The only way you’re going to make make any sort of progress against this attention-hungry app, is by giving it up. Finally, and most obviously, HOW IS THE WEAKER PERSON SUPPOSED TO STOP THE PUNCH? Speaking less in analogies, how is the average user supposed to ‘will’ their way out of a system constructed with so much care and precision, that is designed to serve only a single purpose, which is to hold your attention for a long time? Whether you’re for capitalism or not, you have to admit Adam Smith never thought of the consumers being the products; he never thought that ‘the sins of man’ that were supposed to benefit society (as that was the premise of capitalism) would turn against humankind itself, and would seek to exploit it. This is most definitely a flaw in the system, and you don’t have to be an anti-capitalist to admit it. Now I could go on and on, likening this to slavery or to the dystopian future that George Orwell depicted in his book, 1984, but that would be totally unnecessary, as I only wanted to provide my reasoning behind wanting to dealgorithmize.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;how-am-i-going-to-go-about-dealgorithmizing-on-youtube&quot;&gt;How am I going to go about dealgorithmizing on YouTube?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m going to limit myself to 5 YouTube videos everyday (at least for now). The first 5 videos in my YouTube feed are going to be youtube-dl’ed. Good news is that most of the stuff I watch is pretty informative anyways, so I’m not too worried about downloading anything too unproductive. Music and podcasts will all be listened to on Spotify now. After I download the 5 videos, I’m going to block YouTube on my /etc/hosts file, so that there’s absolutely no chance of me being distracted throughout the day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can already tell this is going to be hard.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">As I listen to a mathematician analyze a Minecraft YouTuber’s speedrun, I think to myself, “Is this the most productive I can be?” And as I begin to reflect upon this question, I try to recollect how I got to this point. The last thing I remembered was being separated from my parents and put into a small cramped room. The people who put me there told me that all I had to do was to look at a screen, and so I did. But I never recalled time passing by so fast; had it really been 20 years?</summary></entry></feed>